[Music]
[âm nhạc]
Hey friend, let me ask you something. The teacher is
Này bạn ơi bạn cho tôi hỏi thầy xôn xao
so strange. What's so fun about that old forest day and
lạ quá rừng già nơi đó có gì vui ngày
night? Crying sadly, I see walking on a rocky path. There's
đêm Khóc man mác thấy đi trên sợi đá cơm
no meat or fish in the pond, only patched things.
thì không thịt cá ao của thịt toàn đồ vá
What's so fun about that?
Có gì đâu mà vui
Why abandon your father and become a monk in the old forest? I
sao thì bỏ ba ba xuất gia trong rừng già
don't understand. Why
không hiểu không
abandon your mother and father and become a monk in the old forest? It's so hard to
thì bỏ mẹ cha xuất gia trong rừng già
understand, so hard to understand.
khó hiểu khó hiểu quá đi
Here, my friends, Thien Nhan, the Buddha
đây các bạn Thiện Nhân ơi Đức Phật đã
taught: "In the first 13 minutes, this path will conquer
dạy Dần 13 phút đầu đà này chiến thắng
everything before your eyes."
mọi trước mắt
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
The disadvantages in life, ignorance in the
thiệt thòi trong cuộc đời vô minh ở nơi
old forest. Turn on the lights day and night, remember on your
chốn rừng già Hãy bật ngày và đêm nhớ
shoulders. Father is sad because he loves all living beings
trên đôi vai Ba buồn vì thương chúng
in the old forest. The teacher is
sinh muôn loài ở nơi chốn rừng già thầy
busy day and night, remembering
bận ngày và đêm nhớ
and letting go because he loves all living beings.
mãi mà buông vì thương chúng sinh muôn
[Music] [
[âm nhạc]
When you meet someone in life, or talk too much, you must be
khi gặp về đời hay nói quá đi thì phải
obedient first. It's so hard,
ngoan trước thật khó quá đi thôi thật
so hard. Life with a girl is fun. Friends near and far, you can smoke cigars. The king is at home. Here, there is still happiness. Life is fun because there is value. Why abandon your mother and father so far away in the old forest? It's so hard, so hard to
sao thì bỏ mẹ cha rất xa nơi rừng già
understand.
khó hiểu khó hiểu quá đi
Now, my friends, be patient and tell the Buddha.  The Buddha
nay các bạn kiên nhẫn nói Đức Phật đã
built 13, starting this path to
xây dựng là 13 bắt đầu đà này chiến
victory, achieving success for the three
thắng ngoài trước mặt thành tựu cho ba
realms from the city, and then speaking of blessings in the
cõi từ Thành qua nói rồi mà phước lành
ten directions, illuminating the Dharma, freeing sentient beings
mười phương sáng soi tranh pháp chúng
from
sinh khỏi miên
suffering in this ignorant life. In the
thiệt thòi trong cuộc đời vô minh ở nơi
ancient forest, I still see Day and Night, remembering and
chốn rừng già thấy vẫn Ngày Và Đêm Nhớ
dividing with golden flowers, because of compassion for all living
chia đôi với hoa vàng vì thương trong
beings. In the ancient forest, I am
sinh muôn loài ở nơi chốn rừng già thì
busy Day and Night, remembering and dividing my shoulders,
bận Ngày Và Đêm Nhớ chia đôi vai mà
because of compassion for all living beings. The five desires of
Vương vì thương trong sinh muôn loài ngũ
life are not lacking, there is
dục đời không thiếu đâu những khổ đau
so much suffering. But, Master, I have understood. The
thật nhiều mà thầy ơi con đã hiểu ra mà
world is far from my parents, I am happy practicing the ascetic Dharma, seeking the
thế giới xa ba má vui tu pháp đầu đà tìm
ancient forest, with boundless compassion for
đến nơi rừng già lòng từ bi bao la vì
all living beings.
chúng sinh khắp muôn loài
For all living beings, there is
vì chúng sinh có
[music]
[âm nhạc]
here, friends, receive
đây các bạn tiếp nhận
this [music], overcoming all obstacles
này chiến thắng mọi chướng ngại
for the three realms. The first, I passed through the mountains, and
cho ba cõi thứ Anh Qua Núi rồi
in life, there is you in the ancient forest, busy during the
trong cuộc đời có mi ở nơi chốn rừng già
day, together on
vì bận ngày vào bên nhau trên đôi môi
green lips, all living beings in the place of birth,
trong xanh muôn loài ở nơi chốn sinh ra
still deluded and together on hurried lips,
vì vẫn mê và bên nhau trên đôi môi vội
because of love.
vàng vì thương
[music]
[âm nhạc]